Guide to the Peabody Museum of Natural History, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Peabody Museum of Natural History, Yale University, records
1866-1990
RU 471
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
21.5
(42 boxes)
The records consist of correspondence, reports, deeds of gifts, inventories, statements, and publications documenting the activities and operations of the Peabody Museum of Natural History at Yale University.
Peabody Museum of Natural History
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 33-A (YRG 33-A), Records of the Peabody Museum of Natural History.
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection as a whole is available for research, parts of it may be restricted due to law, university policy or fragility. Any restricted material will be noted as such.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, reports, deeds of gifts, inventories, statements, and publications documenting the activities and operations of the Peabody Museum of Natural History at Yale University.
College science museums; Natural history museums; Peabody Museum of Natural History; Yale University -- Museums
- Financial records, Circa 1870-1929; Accession 19ND-A-143
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  - Bills and Vouchers
    - 1891-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - 1906 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence [concerning financial and other matters], 1871-1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Shipping materials [bills, invoices], 1898-1899 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Treasurer's Reports
    - 1870, 1872-1878, 1880-1885 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1886, 1888-1906 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - 1907-1916 (Box 3, Folder 13-16)
    - 1917-1929 (Box 4, Folder 17-19)
- Records of the director, Circa 1866-1959; Accession 19ND-A-146
  Materials in box 15 are restricted until January 1, 2035 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - I. Pre 1922 records, including records of George E. Brush and Charles Schuchert, 1866-1926
    - Deeds of Gift, 1866-1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Early Expeditions, 1870-1873 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Account Books, 1873-1891 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Drawer stacks, 1911-1915 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Catalog of Library, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Inventory, 1914-1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Floors, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Halls, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Salaries, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fund, 1917-1921 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - II. Richard S. Lull, 1905-1938
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Association of Museums
      - Correspondence, 1924-1938 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      - Monthly Reports and Newsletter, 1923-1930 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
      - New England Conference, 1926-1929 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Peripatetic Course, 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Smithsonian Training Course, 1926-1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - American Museums Natural History, 1926-1936 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - American Society of Zoologists, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Applicants, 1923-1931 (Box 3, Folder 11-11a)
    - Appointments, 1931-1937 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Associates of the Museum, 1926-1928 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Auditorium and extensions, 1925-1929 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Authority, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - B, 1928-1938 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Background, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Bingham, Hiram Collection, 1922-1930 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Bishop Collection, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Bishop Museum Committee & Fellowship, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Board of Trustees Record Book, 1933-1937 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Brush Collection, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Budget, 1925-1937 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Building Program, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Bulletin, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - C, 1924-1931 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Cardeza Collection, 1922-1929 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Cases, exhibition, 1924-1929 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Casts, 1926-1929 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Children's Department
      - Auxiliary, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Correspondence, 1927-1936 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Hooker House, 1928-1931 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Monthly reports, 1929-1937 (Box 4, Folder 33-34)
      - Staff meetings, 1930-1937 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Collections and material offered, 1926-1929 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Committee and Council, 1921-1931 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Complaints, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Cornerstone, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Curator's meetings, 1923-1937 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
    - Curator's reports (supplementary), 1925-1937 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Cypress swamp, 1923-1925 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Darby Expedition, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Day, George Parmly, 1923-1936 (Box 5, Folder 45-46)
    - Departmental reports, 1931-1932 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - deTerra, Helmut, 1931-1936 (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
    - Duplicate materials in the Museum, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 50-51)
    - Egyptian material, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Equipment, 1924-1926 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Exchange requests, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Executive Committee, 1930-1933 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - F, 1932-1934 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Farnham, Thomas W., 1923-1936 (Box 6, Folder 57-58)
    - Fossil fields reports, 1923-1928 (Box 6, Folder 59-60)
    - Guide, re, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Hall of Fame, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 62-63)
    - Hotchkiss House, 1933-1937 (Box 6, Folder 64-65)
    - K, 1935-1938 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Klauder, Charles Z., 1930 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Knight, Charles R., 1925-1929 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Labels, 1925-1930 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Lectures: subjects, 1924-1930 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Letters of introduction given to members of staff, 1929-1931 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Lewis, Edward G., 1928-1937 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Library, 1923-1935 (Box 6, Folder 73-74)
    - Lighting, undated (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Loans of material and equipment, 1920-1926 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Loan requests, 1924-1928 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Lohmann, C.A., 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Longwell, Professor, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - M, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - MacCurdy, George G., 1923-1929 (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Mailing list, re, 1926-1927 (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Pope Mastodon, 1913-1925 (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Memorial Tablets, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Monoclonius skeleton, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Mounting, undated (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Moving, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Museums, other, 1916-1923 (Box 7, Folder 88-89)
    - N, 1924-1926 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Offices and furniture, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Organization, 1909-1922 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Osgood, Cornelius, 1931-1937 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - P, 1926-1936 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Peabody - Bishop Museum relationship, 1920-1930 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Pendulum, 1925-1937 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Photographic material, 1923-1926 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - Photographs and printed matter, requests for, 1925-1926 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Picture and notes: old Peabody Museum, undated (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - Photos of design: Peabody Museum, undated (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - Porter, Mildred, 1932-1937 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - Portraits and other paintings, 1925-1933 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Postcards, 1926-1927 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Preperator's room and equipment, 1922-1924 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Publicity, 1923-1931 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Purpose and scope of museum, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Rainey, Froelich G., 1934-1937 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Ringling Brothers, 1923-1934 (Box 8, Folder 108-109)
    - S, 1931-1935 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Sapir, Edward, 1931-1934 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Schuchert, Charles, 1905-1935 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Seymour, Charles, 1937-1938 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Smithsonian Institution, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Specifications, 1922-1924 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Staff, 1924-1933 (Box 9, Folder 116-117)
    - Storage Shed: box contents, 1906-1923 (Box 9, Folder 118)
    - Storages, 1922-1923 (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - Technician, 1930-1937 (Box 9, Folder 120)
    - Thorpe, Malcolm, 1933-1937 (Box 9, Folder 121)
    - Transparencies (Bush, Frederick), 1925-1929 (Box 9, Folder 122)
    - "Tree of Life" (exhibit photograph), 1929 (Box 9, Folder 123)
    - Trustees meetings, 1924-1937 (Box 9, Folder 124-125)
    - Visits: classes, clubs, 1926-1930 (Box 9, Folder 126)
    - W, 1923-1935 (Box 9, Folder 127)
    - Weaver, Charles E., 1923-1935 (Box 9, Folder 128)
  - III. Albert E. Parr, 1910-1945
    - Advisory Committee, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Advisory Council, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Alumni Day, 1939-1942 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Applicants, 1938-1945 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Library and Museums, committee on, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - School Service Department: monthly reports, 1938-1941 (Box 10, Folder 6-9)
    - Tyrannosaurus rex, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Seismograph, 1910-1938 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - IV. Carl O. Dunbar, 1924-1958
    - Accident reports, 1934-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Acknowledgments, 1937-1957 (Box 11, Folder 2-6)
    - Bradley Smith Incorporated, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Bulletin #5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1948-1955 (Box 11, Folder 8-12)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Counter orders and other purchases, 1953-1958 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Employment, Temporary, 1955-1956 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Insurance claims, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Inventory, 1924-1952 (Box 12, Folder 18-20)
    - John Wiley and Sons, Incorporated, 1950-1957 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Library and Museums, Council on, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Paynter, Raymond: Mexican Trip, 1941-1951 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Petty cash, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Publications, 1953-1958 (Box 13, Folder 25-26)
    - School Service Department: reports, 1951-1952 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Sellright Giftwares Corporation, 1950-1958 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Simon and Schuster, 1956-1958 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - Smithsonian, 1957-1958 (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - Statements, 1956-1958 (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Stationary orders, 1925-1955 (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - Tax on publications sold, 1948-1958 (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - Wards Natural Science Establishment, Incorporated: Mineral Collector's Guide, 1953-1957 (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - V. Annual Reports, 1923-1947
    - Director's reports
      - 1923-1932 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - 1931-1947 (Box 14, Folder 2-17)
    - Curator's reports
      - 1937-1947 (Box 14, Folder 18-25)
  - VI. Student records and corporation votes, 1923-1959
    - Bursary students, 1938-1959 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
    - Corporation votes, 1923-1939 (Box 15, Folder 3-5)
- Correspondence of the director, Circa 1918-1956; Accession 1969-A-007
  Scope and Contents
  Carl Owen Dunbar, BA Univ Kansas 1913; PhD Yale Univ 1917. Asst Geology 1917-1918, James Dwight Dana Research Fellow 1917-1918; Asst Prof Historical Geology 1920-1927, Assoc Prof 1927-1930; Prof Paleontology and Stratigraphy 1930-1959, Emeritus 1959-; Acting Chn Dept Geology 2d term 1958-1959; Asst Curator Invertebrate Paleontology 1920-1926, Curator 1926-1959, Emeritus 1959-; Dir Peabody Museum of Natural History 1942-1959, Emeritus 1959-; (Calhoun Coll 1956-).
  - Correspondence files, 1918-1956
    - A
      - 1924-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - B
      - 1920-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6-12)
    - C
      - 1933-1940 (Box 3, Folder 13-20)
      - 1941-1956 (Box 4, Folder 21-27)
    - D
      - 1924-1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - 1938-1956 (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
    - E-F
      - 1918-1944 (Box 5, Folder 31-35)
      - 1945-1956 (Box 6, Folder 36-38)
      - 1922-1950 (Box 6, Folder 39-40)
      - 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - H-I-J
      - 1944-1945 (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - 1921-1930 (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - 1931-1933 (Box 7, Folder 44)
      - 1935-1943 (Box 7, Folder 45-51)
      - 1944-1946 (Box 7, Box 8, Folder 52)
      - 1948-1956 (Box 8, Folder 53-55)
    - K-L
      - 1921-1931 (Box 8, Folder 56-60)
      - 1932-1942 (Box 9, Folder 61-69)
      - 1943-1947 (Box 10, Folder 70-73)
      - 1949-1956 (Box 10, Folder 74-78)
    - M
      - 1924-1947 (Box 11, Folder 79-86)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 12, Folder 87)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 12, Folder 88)
    - N-O
      - 1929-1956 (Box 12, Folder 89-95)
    - P-Q
      - 1922-1956 (Box 13, Folder 96-99)
    - R
      - 1922-1945 (Box 13, Folder 100-103)
      - 1946-1956 (Box 14, Folder 104-105)
    - S
      - 1922-1937 (Box 14, Folder 106-111)
      - 1938-1951 (Box 15, Folder 112-120)
      - 1952-1956 (Box 16, Folder 121-122)
    - T-U-V
      - 1922-1940 (Box 16, Folder 123-130)
      - 1941-1956 (Box 17, Folder 131-137)
    - W
      - 1921-1936 (Box 17, Folder 138-141)
      - 1937-1946 (Box 18, Folder 142-149)
      - 1947-1956 (Box 19, Folder 150-152)
    - Y-Z
      - 1923-1956 (Box 19, Folder 153)
- Records of Kwang-Chih Chang as curator of Anthropology, 1961-1978; Accession 2007-A-143
  Access is restricted to Office of Origin only.
  - Traditional China Seminar, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Yale University Miscellaneous, 1962-1974 (Box 1)
  - Degree Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Junior Faculty Fellowships, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - International Studies Misc., 1961-1969 (Box 1)
  - Southeast Asia Studies, 1961-1975 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee, 1971-1977 (Box 1)
  - PM Centennial, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Social Science Advisory Committee, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Archaeology, 1963-1977 (Box 1)
  - Archaeology Lab, 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - Early China Subcommittee, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Molly Ho correspondence, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Social Science Studies of China Subcommittee, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Peabody Museum Curator's Meetings, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - HEW ideas, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Library, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Appts, applicants for, 1968-1975 (Box 1)
  - Appointments, Social Science, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Yale Peabody Museum, 1962-1972 (Box 1)
  - CEAS [Council on East Asian Studies], 1961-1978 (Box 1)
  - Boards of Permanent Officers, Joint Meetings, including CVs, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Peabody Annual Reports, misc, Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - East Asia Colloquium, 1963-1969 (Box 1)
  - Japanese Exhibition, 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - East Asia Ideas, 1965-1970 (Box 1)
  - Curator's Minutes, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Curator's Minutes, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Chairmanship, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - DUS [Director of Undergraduate Studies], 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - DGS [Director of Graduate Studies], 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Yale Department Meetings, 1961-1969 (Box 2)
  - Yale Faculty Meetings, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Yale Department Reports, 1962-1968 (Box 2)
  - Yale Department Miscellaneous, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - Asiatics, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Faculty, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Richard, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
  - Henderson, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Hole, 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - Student Affairs, 1962-1973 (Box 2)
  - Department Meetings, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - [Chinese] Seminar, n.d. (Box 2)
  - DUS, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
- Director search committee records, 1988-1990; Accession 2009-A-065
  Access prohibited for the life of Alison Richard plus five years or 75 years after she left Yale, whichever is longer.
  - Anthropology faculty, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curators, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agendas and attachments from meetings, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - working papers, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Peabody info, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)